"Does Sunscreen Cause or Prevent Skin Cancer?"
Decades ago,
studies started bubbling up,
reporting that not only
was the use of sunscreen
not found to be protective
against skin cancer,
but it was associated with
significantly elevated risk.
But subsequent studies offered
the obvious explanation
of this paradox.
People who use sunscreen are
more likely to be sunbathers.
That's like finding those
who use motorcycle helmets
are more likely to die
on the highway.
It's not that sunscreen
and helmets aren't protective;
it's just
that they're associated
with engagement
in risky activities.
But you don't know,
until you put it to the test.
As I noted in my last video,
randomized controlled trials
have shown that regular use
of sunscreen
can arrest visible signs
of skin aging,
including
biopsy-proven reductions
in UV-related skin damage.
But are there
interventional trials
proving sunscreen
can prevent cancer?
Yes.
Organ transplant recipients
are highly susceptible
to skin cancers
because they have to be given
immune suppressants
to prevent organ rejection.
A group of 120 organ recipients
were equally informed
about sun protection measures,
but half were given free
broad spectrum
SPF 50+ sunscreen
for daily application
to their head, neck,
forearms, and hands.
After two years, there were
nine new basal carcinomas
in the control group
versus only two
in the sunscreen group.
That sounds good, but it may
have just been a fluke.
In contrast, there was
a highly significant difference
in the proportion of patients
who got new invasive
squamous cell carcinomas.
Eight new cases
in the control group
versus zero
in the sunscreen group.
But wait until you hear
about what happened
to their actinic keratoses,
the precancerous growths
that can turn into skin cancer.
They all started out
covered in them,
a total of 191 detected
in each group.
In the subsequent 24 months,
the control group
developed 82 new ones.
How many did
the sunscreen group develop?
Negative 102.
More than 100
precancerous growths
in the sunscreen group
spontaneously regressed
and vanished completely
(compared to 82 new growths
developing in the control group
without a single one
disappearing).
Their bodies, even in
their immunocompromised state,
could heal itself
once it just stopped
being bombarded with
so many cancer-causing rays.
Other randomized
controlled trials
have shown similar findings,
but generalizability
is limited.
The studies all used
high-risk populations,
for example, those living
in subtropical climates,
or with a personal history
of precancerous lesions.
So, cancer prevention efficacy
in the general population
would be expected to be less.
On the other hand, the studies
could also have underestimated
the impact since they were
relatively short-term
(not exceeding four years)
and, ethically, had to allow
the control group participants
to slather on
their own sunscreen,
which would dilute
the difference between groups.
For maximum effectiveness,
sunscreen needs to be
applied properly,
which apparently rarely happens
in the real world.
In a study of nearly 5,000
skiers and snowboarders,
almost no one,
only about 4 percent
were fully compliant
with sunscreen recommendations.
First, there's the amount.
The FDA standard
is two milligrams
per square centimeter.
What does that mean?
Use the teaspoon rule:
one teaspoon for your face,
head and neck,
one for the front
of your torso,
another for your back,
one teaspoon for each arm
and two teaspoons for each leg.
That's a total
of nine teaspoons.
That's about
the total volume equivalent
of a golf ball or shot glass,
to help you visualize it.
Unfortunately,
the average sunscreen user
may only apply a quarter
of the recommended amount.
This is why high SPF sunscreens
are often recommended,
like 50+ SPF.
Although the FDA recommends
a minimum SPF of only 15
to prevent skin cancer,
under normal
consumer conditions,
even an SPF of 50
may effectively give you
only an SPF of 12.5,
because most people
don't put on enough.
Randomized double-blind,
head-to-head,
split-face experiments,
where you're randomized
to apply one sunscreen
to one side of your face
and another sunscreen
to the other side,
show that in real life use,
SPF 100+ sunscreen works
significantly better
than SPF 50+ sunscreen.
More than 50 percent
of the participants
were sunburned more
on their SPF 50+ side
compared to only
about 5 percent
on their SPF 100+ side.
Now, a potential downside
of higher SPF sunscreens
is that they could provide
a false sense of security.
Those randomized
to an SPF 30 sunscreen
ended up spending
more cumulative time in the sun
than those receiving
an SPF 10 sunscreen,
as much as five times longer
in some cases.
What else?
Well, people tend to remember
to use sunscreen
on a sunny day at the beach,
but sun protection is needed
even on cloudy days,
since the UV rays
are not dampened
as much as visible light.
There's even a phenomenon
known as "cloud enhancement"
where overcast skies
can sometimes result
in even more UV reaching
the Earth's surface
compared to clear skies.
Sunscreen labels often suggest
waiting at least 15 minutes
after application
before going outdoors,
but when put to the test,
sunscreen was found
to start working immediately
with the full effect apparent
by minute ten.
However, if water resistance
is required,
it may be prudent to wait
the full 15 to 30 minutes
after application
before taking a dip.
The terms "waterproof"
or "sweatproof"
appear to be
meaningless marketing,
as no difference
in retention was noted
between "waterproof" products
and those that were
merely labeled
"water-resistant."
Both were better than
non-water-resistant products,
though,
which lost nearly
all their protective effects
within 20 minutes
of water immersion.
The suggestion that sunscreen
should be reapplied
every two to three hours
only applies under conditions
in which it is rinsed off
by water or sweat,
or rubbed off by friction
from clothing or sand.
Even after allowing sunscreen
to dry first for 20 minutes,
between 15 and 60 percent
of its protective effect
can be lost
after contact with sand.
Otherwise, if the recommended
amount is applied
and the sunscreen layer
is not disturbed,
SPF can be maintained
for as long as eight hours.